<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf8"?>
<chapter>
<title>HTTP</title>
<para>
The Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) is an application protocol for distributed, collaborative, hypermedia information systems. 
HTTP is the foundation of data communication for the World Wide Web, where hypertext documents include hyperlinks to other resources that the user can easily access, for example by a mouse click or by tapping the screen in a web browser.
</para>
<para>ULFS currently supply HTTP-clients for software, HTTP-clients for users called web-browsers and HTTP-servers called web-servers.</para>
<para>It should mentioned that ULFS Packages system uses HTTP protocol to install source packages.</para>
<sect1>
<title>Text web-browser</title>
<para>Web-browsers which can run in text-mode (terminals, consoles) called text web-browsers.</para>
<para>ULFS user can use Links as text web-browser in case graphical system not installed or can't to be used.</para>
<para>To install Links web-browser you can run
<programlisting>
chimp install links
</programlisting></para>
<para>To open website in text browser you can run
<programlisting>
links http://umvirt.com
</programlisting></para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Graphical web-browser</title>
<para>Web-browsers which can run in graphical-mode called graphical web-browsers.</para>
<para>ULFS user can use NetSurf as graphical web-browser in case graphical system is installed.</para>
<para>To install NetSurf web-browser you can run
<programlisting>
chimp install netsurf
</programlisting></para>
<para>To open website in text browser you can run
<programlisting>
nsgtk http://umvirt.com
</programlisting></para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Apache web-server</title>
<para>Apache HTTPd is most popular Web-server which can be used to hosting static and dynamic web-sites.</para>
<para>Apache HTTPd can be used to host ULFS Packages service in your local area network in case no Internet connection available.</para>
<para>To install Apache  HTTPd web-browser you can run
<programlisting>
chimp install httpd
</programlisting></para>
<para>To place openssh-server on autoload you have to run command:
<programlisting>
cd /usr/share/blfs-systemd-units
sudo make install-httpd
</programlisting></para>

</sect1>

</chapter>
