<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf8"?>
<chapter>
<title>SSH</title>
<para>Secure Shell (SSH) is a cryptographic network protocol for operating network services securely over an unsecured network. 
SSH can be used for logging into a remote machine and for executing commands on a remote machine.</para>
<para>In ULFS like in popular GNU/Linux distributions OpenSSH is main SSH protocol implementation.</para>
<para>OpenSSH can be also used for:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>File transfer via scp utility or external applications like Midnight Comander, Rsync and others.</listitem>
<listitem>Port forwarding from remote machine to local and vice versa.</listitem>
<listitem>Automated configuration with Ansible tool.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
<sect1>
<title>OpenSSH installation</title>
<para>To install openssh client and server you have to type: <programlisting>chimp install openssh</programlisting></para>
<para>To place openssh-server on autoload you have to run command:
<programlisting>
cd /usr/share/blfs-systemd-units
sudo make install-sshd
</programlisting></para>
<para>After running bellowing command you have to reboot to check OpenSSH-server autoloading. OpenSSH-server process sshd have to be started and incoming connections on 22 TCP port have to be acceped.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Connecting to SSH-server</title>
<para>Connection to SSH-server is performing by command  <programlisting>ssh %username%@%server%</programlisting></para>
<para>Where %username% is user name on server, %server% is server name or IP-address.</para>
If you want to be able to log in without typing in your password, first create ~/.ssh/id_rsa and ~/.ssh/id_rsa.pub with ssh-keygen and then copy ~/.ssh/id_rsa.pub to ~/.ssh/authorized_keys on the remote computer that you want to log into. You'll need to change REMOTE_USERNAME and REMOTE_HOSTNAME for the username and hostname of the remote computer and you'll also need to enter your password for the ssh-copy-id command to succeed:
<programlisting>
ssh-keygen &amp;&amp;
ssh-copy-id -i ~/.ssh/id_rsa.pub REMOTE_USERNAME@REMOTE_HOSTNAME
</programlisting>
</sect1>

</chapter>
