<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf8"?>
<chapter>
<title>Virtualization</title>
<para>Virtualization is the technology which allows to run multiple virtual computers (virtual machines, guests, VMs) on one real computer(host). ULFS have a virtualization support it can be used both on VMs and on Hosts.</para>
<para>ULFS provides specific virtualization software vision. Some virtualization platforms is not open-source (VmWare, Microsoft Hyper-V, Parrallels) some of open-source virtualization software have big issues (VirtualBox, Docker).</para>
<para>Virtualization software provided in ULFS is open-source and don't have big issues.</para>

<sect1>
<title>Linux containers</title>
<para>Linux containers (LXC) is technology of spliting physical computer environment to multiple virtual with same Linux kernel. LXC have best performance but provide limitations.</para>
<para>To install Linux containers (LXC) you can run
<programlisting>
chimp install lxc
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>Warning: Linux kernel sources should be available and ready for modules compilation. Please check it before install.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>QEMU</title>
<para>QEMU also known as KVM (Kernvel Virtual Machine) is powerful emulator which can run virtual machines on various platforms and operating systems: GNU/Linux, Microsoft Windows, KolibriOS, Haiku, ReactOS and others.</para>
<para>Warning: running Appple MacOS VMs is not supported. Running hacked versions of MacOS X (Hackintosh) is not recommended.</para>
<para>To install QEMU you can run
<programlisting>
chimp install qemu
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>Warning: KVM support should be enabled in Linux Kernel.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Libvirt</title>
<para>Libvirt is virtualization API which simplify and controls virtualization proccess.</para>
<para>To install Libvirt you can run
<programlisting>
chimp install libvirt
</programlisting>
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Virt-manager</title>
<para>Virt-manager is GUI-fronted for libvirt. Virt-manager is simplify virtualization process.</para>
<para>To install virt-manager you can run
<programlisting>
chimp install virt-manager
</programlisting>
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>SPICE</title>
<para>SPICE is complete open source solution for remote access to virtual machines in a seamless way so you can play videos, record audio, share usb devices and share folders without complications.</para>
<para>Spice server is integrated in QEMU. To install spice-client you can run
<programlisting>
chimp install spice-gtk
</programlisting>
</para>
</sect1>


<sect1>
<title>FlexVDI SPICE</title>
<para>FlexVDI SPICE is improved version of SPICE. FlexVDI spice is allows VMs to use client's Internet connection via proxy-servers. Using client's Internet connection allow to eliminate risc of client abuse on Internet connection.</para>
<para>FlexVDI Spice server is not integrated in QEMU. To install it you shoud install qemu as usual then you have to run:
<programlisting>
chimp install flexvdi-spice-protocol
chimp install flexvdi-spice
chimp install flexvdi-quemu
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>To install FlexVDI Spice client you can run
<programlisting>
chimp install flexvdi-spice-gtk
</programlisting>
</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
